Welcome. This is xAI NetBeans, an agentic coding assistant
powered by xAI's Grok model, embedded directly inside the
Apache NetBeans I-D-E. In the next few minutes, we'll
walk through its architecture, end to end.
First, what exactly is this module?
xAI NetBeans is a NetBeans Platform module. It adds a xAI
Assistant tool window where you chat with Grok. Grok can read
your project, search it, and, in agent modes, create and edit
files. Everything flows through an OpenAI-compatible function-calling loop.
Under the hood, it's Java 17, built against NetBeans
release 240, using the J-D-K's built-in HttpClient, Gson for
J-SON, and commonmark for rendering the transcript.
Let's see how the pieces fit together.
At the top is the Xai Assistant Top Component, the tool window that
hosts multiple tabs. Each tab is a Session Panel, one independent chat session.
A session owns a Transcript for the conversation view, an Agent Engine that
drives the agent, and it reads the settings at runtime.
The Agent Engine is the heart of the module. It holds
the conversation history and coordinates three things: the Xai Client that
talks to the Grok API, a Tool Registry of five callable
tools, and the system prompt for the current mode.
The code is organized into five packages.
The api package handles H-T-T-P transport and the wire data
model. core holds the Mode enum, the system prompts, and
the Agent Engine loop. settings stores configuration in NetBeans preferences
and adds the Options panel. tools contains the tool implementations,
the registry, and path resolution. And u-i is the tool
window, the session panel, and the transcript.
What Grok is allowed to do depends on the mode.
There are five modes. Ask, Plan, and Debug are read-only.
They expose three safe tools and never modify files. Agent
and Multitask are read-write. They expose all five tools and
can edit your project, with Multitask running across parallel tabs.
One important detail: switching the mode builds a brand-new
engine, with a fresh prompt and an empty history.
Now, the tools themselves.
Grok can call five tools. read file, list dir, and search are
read-only; they inspect your project. write file and edit file are mutating.
write file creates or overwrites a file, and edit file makes an
exact string replacement. Both require your approval before they touch disk.
This brings us to the agent loop, the core of how a turn runs.
When you send a prompt, your message is appended to
the history. The engine then calls the Grok API with
the history and the tools allowed by your mode.
If the response contains no tool calls, the turn
is done, and you get the final answer.
But if Grok requests tool calls, the engine dispatches each one,
checking approval, executing it, and refreshing the I-D-E. It appends the
results to the history and calls the model again.
This repeats until Grok stops asking for tools,
up to a default of twenty-five iterations. Note
that every single call sends the entire history.
A quick word on threading.
All user-interface work happens on the Swing event dispatch thread: input,
the transcript, and approval dialogs. The agent turn, the blocking H-T-T-P
call, and tool execution run on a background Request Processor pool
with eight threads, so up to eight tabs can work at
once. Callbacks are marshalled back to the U-I thread.
When a mutating tool needs approval, it blocks its background thread
and waits while the dialog is shown. That's the approval bridge.
Finally, some deliberate design choices and limits.
The client is non-streaming; a turn blocks until the full response
arrives. There's no editor integration: edits go straight to disk and
are surfaced with a file refresh. There's no command execution, only
the five filesystem tools. Search uses regex over files rather than
the I-D-E index. Conversations aren't persisted across restarts. And approval intentionally
blocks the agent until you decide.
And that's the architecture, end to end: from the U-I, through the
Agent Engine, to Grok, to the tools, and finally to your files.
For all the details, see the architecture markdown file. Thanks for watching.